<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="PA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main">&quot;Literary Women No. II. Jane Austen.&quot;</title>
				<title type="subordinate">from <title><hi rendition="#italics">The Athen&#230;um
						</hi></title></title>
				<author type="writer">
					<name>Maria Jane Jewsbury</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
					<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Co-Editor</resp>
					<name>Krystal J. Iseminger</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>JewsburyAustenRev1831</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a">Literary Women No. II. Jane Austen</title>
						<author type="writer">Jewsbury, Maria, 1800-1833 </author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j">The Athenæum</title>
						<imprint>
							<date when="1831-08-27">27 August 1831</date>
							<biblScope unit="issue">200</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page">553-4</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “, " for ”, '
						for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
					<p>Quotation marks that indicate block quotes have been silently eliminated.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
					<p>Compositors' catchwords and running titles have been silently eliminated.</p>
					<p>Long "s" (&#383;) has been silently modernized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>ARC Genre Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Advertisement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Animation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Catalog</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Chronology</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Essay</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Film, Documentary</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Film, Experimental</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Film, Narrative</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Film, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Historiography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Interview</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Liturgy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Musical Analysis</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Music, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Musical Work</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Musical Score</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Nonficition</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Performance</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Political Statement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g35">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g36">
						<catDesc>Scripture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g37">
						<catDesc>Sermon</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g38">
						<catDesc>Speech</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g39">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g40">
						<catDesc>Travel Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g41">
						<catDesc>Unspecified</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g42">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
					xml:id="f">
					<bibl>ARC Format Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="f1">
						<catDesc>Codex</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f2">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f3">
						<catDesc>Dataset</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f4">
						<catDesc>Drawing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f5">
						<catDesc>Illustration</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f6">
						<catDesc>Interactive Resource</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f7">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f8">
						<catDesc>Map</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f9">
						<catDesc>Moving Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f10">
						<catDesc>Notated Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f11">
						<catDesc>Page Proofs</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f12">
						<catDesc>Pamphlet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f13">
						<catDesc>Periodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f14">
						<catDesc>Physcial Object</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f15">
						<catDesc>Roll</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f16">
						<catDesc>Sheet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f17">
						<catDesc>Sound</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f18">
						<catDesc>Still Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f19">
						<catDesc>Typescript</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#lcsh">
					<list type="simple">
						<item>Criticism</item>
						<item>Life Writing</item>
						<item>Essay</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="#g9 #g20 #g12" scheme="#g"/>
				<catRef target="#f13" scheme="#f"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<date>2018-07-15</date>
				<list>
					<item>revise TEI encoding</item>
					<item>document ID change</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name xml:id="KI"> Krystal J. Iseminger</name>
				<date>2017-02-05</date>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change>
				<name xml:id="MW">Mary A. Waters</name>
				<date>2010-12-01</date>
				<list>
					<item>Created Edition</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head><bibl><author type="writer"><name><ref target="people.html#JewsburyMaria"
									>Maria Jane Jewsbury</ref></name></author>
						<title type="main" level="a">LITERARY WOMEN No. II.<hi rendition="#sup"
									><note place="foot">For No.I. <ref
										target="people.html#HemansFelicia">Mrs.
									Hemans</ref>&#8212;see <title>Athena&#230;um</title>, No. 172
										[<hi rendition="#italics"><title>Athena&#230;um</title></hi>
									note].</note></hi><lb/><ref target="people.html#AustenJane">JANE
								AUSTEN</ref>.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><title
										level="j"><hi rendition="#italics">The
										Athen&#230;um</hi></title> no. 200 (August 27, 1831): 553-4.
									This edition created by Krystal J. Iseminger and Mary A.
									Waters.</note></hi></title></bibl></head>

				<p>I<hi rendition="#smcaps">n</hi> the slight sketches which will from time to time
					occupy a page of the <title><hi rendition="#italics">
					Athen&#230;um</hi></title>, we shall alternate between the dead and the living,
					the past time and the present, and thus tincture criticism with biography. Would
					that the interesting and gifted woman whose name is prefixed to this paper,
					could be numbered among the living! Would that, instead of closing her works
					with the saddened feeling, that the source whence so much pure amusement
					emanated is sealed for ever, we could glance over the list of books &quot;nearly
					ready for publication,&quot; and find another announced by the same author. <ref
						target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>, however, has been dead
					fourteen years; and from what has been laid before the public of a biographical
					nature, (slight as that is,) there seldom appears to have been a more beautiful
					accordance between an author&apos;s life and writings; in fact, in the life and
					education of <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>, may be
					discerned many of the causes of the excellencies that mark her works. Her father
					was a clergyman, a scholar, a man of fine general taste, and for forty years he
					resided on his living, (Steventon, in Hants,) conscientiously discharging its
					ministerial duties in his own person. <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss
						Austen</ref> was thus placed from infancy under two influences, calculated
					to mature female intellect in the happiest manner&#8212;rural life, and domestic
					intercourse at once polished, intellectual, and affectionate. The four years
					prior to his death were spent at Bath; and after that event, she resided with
					her mother and sister in the pleasant village of Shawton, Hants; from thence she
					sent her novels into the world, and there, in May 1817, she died, after a slow
					insidious decline of many months. She was only forty-two when this event
					occurred, and though some of her works had been the gradual composition of her
					previous life, she was upwards of thirty before the first (&apos;Sense and
					Sensibility&apos;) was published. For those who may doubt the possibility of
					engrafting literary habits on those peculiarly set apart for the female sex, and
					for those who may doubt how far literary reputation is attainable, without a
					greater sacrifice to notoriety than they may deem compatible with female
					happiness and delicacy, it is pleasant to have so triumphant a reference as <ref
						target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>. Being dead, she may be
					quoted without impropriety. Placed by Providence in easy and elegant
					circumstances&#8212;endowed preeminently with good sense, and a placid
					unobtrusive temperament, she passed unscathed through the ordeals of authorship,
					and, in addition to exciting enthusiastic affection in immediate friends,
					received the general good-will of all who knew her. This alone is a high tribute
					to the benevolence of her temper, and the polish of her manners in daily life;
					for in print, her peculiar forte is delineating folly, selfishness, and
					absurdity&#8212;especially in her own sex. In society, she had too much wit to
					lay herself open to the charge of being too witty; and discriminated too well to
					attract notice to her discrimination. She was, we suspect, like one of her own
					heroines, &quot;incurably gentle,&quot; and acted on the principle of another,
					that &quot;if a women have the misfortune of knowing anything, she should
					conceal it as well as she can.&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">See
								<ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Austen</ref>&apos;s <title><hi
									rendition="#italics">Northanger Abbey</hi></title>, Chapter 14
							for her ironic use of this same courtesy-book style injunction.
							&quot;Incurably gentle&quot; is <ref target="people.html#AustenJane"
								>Austen</ref>&apos;s description of Fanny Price in <hi
								rendition="#italics"><title>Mansfield Park</title></hi> Chapter
							33.</note></hi> Besides this, whilst literature was a delightful
					occupation, it was not a profession to <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss
						Austen</ref>; she was not irrational enough to despise reputation and profit
					when they sought her, but she became an authoress entirely from taste and
					inclination; and as her judgment made her severely critical before she published
					her works, her unambitious temper was amply satisfied with the attention
					bestowed upon them by the public.</p>
				<p>Unlike that of many writers, <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss
						Austen</ref>&amp;s fame has grown fastest since she died; there was no <hi
						rendition="#italics">&#233;clat</hi> about her first, or second, or third
					appearance; the public took time to make up its mind; and she, not having staked
					her hopes of happiness on success or failure, and not being obliged by
					circumstances to stake something more tangible on these results, could afford to
					wait for the decision of her claims. Those claims have long been established
					beyond a question; but the merit of <hi rendition="#italics">first</hi>
					recognizing them, belongs less to reviewers than to general readers.</p>
				<p>The able article in the <title><hi rendition="#italics">Quarterly
						Review</hi></title> for 1821, was founded on a posthumous work, when the
					praise or blame of ten thousand critics were equally unimportant to the author.
					So retired, so unmarked by literary notoriety, was the life <ref
						target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref> led, that if any likeness
					was ever taken of her, (and the contrary supposition would seem strange,) none
					has ever been engraved; and of no woman, whose writings are as numerous and
					distinguished, is there perhaps so little public beyond the circle of those who
					knew her when alive&#8212; <quote><lg type="stanza">
							<l>A violet by a mossy stone</l>
							<l>Half hidden from the eye.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
											target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>,
											<title>&quot;Song&quot;</title> (&quot;She dwelt among
										th&apos; untrodden ways&quot;) 5-6.</note></hi></l>
						</lg></quote></p>
				<p>With regard to her genius, we must adventure a few remarks. She herself compares
					her productions to a little bit of ivory two inches wide, worked upon with a
					brush so fine that little effect is produced after much labour.<hi
						rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref target="people.html#AustenJane"
								>Austen</ref>&apos;s famous description of her work as &quot;The
							little bit (two Inches wide) of Ivory on which I work with so fine a
							Brush, as produces little effect after much labour,&quot; which so
							powerfully influenced the reception of her work, appears in her 16-17
							December 1816 letter to James Edward Austen.</note></hi> It is so; her
					portraits are perfect likenesses, admirably finished, many of them gems, but it
					is all miniature-painting; and, satisfied with being inimitable in one line, she
					never essayed canvas and oils&#8212;never tried her hand at a majestic daub. Her
					&quot;two inches of ivory&quot; just describes her preparations for a tale of
					three volumes. A village&#8212;two families connected together&#8212;three or
					four interlopers, out of whom are to spring a little <hi rendition="#italics"
						>tracaserie</hi>&#8212;a village or a country town, and by means of village
					and country town visiting and gossiping, a real plot shall thicken, and its
					&quot;rear of darkness&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
								target="people.html#MiltonJohn"
								>Milton</ref>,<title>&quot;L&apos;Allegro&quot;</title> (1654)
							50.</note></hi> never be scattered till six pages off <hi
						rendition="#italics">Finis</hi>.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
							>Compare the phrasing with <ref target="people.html#AustenJane"
								>Austen</ref>&apos;s declaration that &quot;3 or 4 Families in a
							Country Village is the very thing to work on&quot; (Letter to Anna
							Austen, 9-18 September 1814).</note></hi> The plots are simple in
					construction, and yet intricate in developement;&#8212;the main characters,
					those that the reader feels sure are to love, marry, and make mischief, are
					introduced in the first or second chapter; the work is all done by half a dozen
					people; no person, scene, or sentence, is ever introduced needless to the matter
					in hand&#8212;no catastrophes, or discoveries, or surprises of a grand nature
					are allowed&#8212;neither children nor fortunes are lost or found by
					accident&#8212;the mind is never taken off the level surface of life&#8212;the
					reader breakfasts, dines, walks, and gossips, with the various worthies, till a
					process of transmutation takes place in him, and he absolutely fancies himself
					one of the company. Yet the winding up of the plots involves a surprise; a few
					incidents are entangled at the beginning in the most simple and natural manner,
					and till the close one never feels quite sure how they are to be disentangled.
					Disentangled, however, they are, and that in a most satisfactory manner. The
					secret is, <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref> was a thorough
					mistress in the knowledge of human character; how it is acted upon by education
					and circumstance; and how, when once formed, it shows itself through every hour
					of every day, and in every speech to every person. Her conversations would be
					tiresome but for this; and her personages, the fellows to whom may be met in the
					streets or drank tea with at half an hour&apos;s notice, would excite no
					interest. But in <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>n&apos;s
					hands we see into their hearts and hopes, their motives, their struggles within
					themselves; and a sympathy is induced, which, if extended to daily life and the
					world at large, would make the reader a more amiable person. We think some of
					Miss Austen&apos;s works deficient in delineations of a high cast of character,
					in an exalted tone of thought and feeling, a religious bias that can be seen as
					well as understood; <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>
					seemed afraid of imparting imagination to her favourites, and conceived good
					sense the <hi rendition="#italics">ultima Thule</hi><hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot">In ancient Greek and Latin times, Thule was believed the
							most northern place in the world. Hence, <hi rendition="#italics">ultima
								Thule</hi> is the farthest possible limit of discovery and travel
								(<hi rendition="#italics"><title>Oxford English
								Dictionary</title></hi>).</note></hi> of moral possessions. Good
					sense <hi rendition="#italics">is</hi> very good, but St. Leon&apos;s
					Marguerite, and Rebecca, and Desdemona,<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
							>Characters from <ref target="people.html#GodwinWilliam">William
								Godwin</ref>&apos;s <title><hi rendition="#italics">St. Leon: A Tale
									of the Sixteenth Century</hi></title> (1799), Sir <ref
								target="people.html#ScottWalter">Walter Scott</ref>&apos;s
									<title><hi rendition="#italics">Ivanhoe</hi></title> (1819), and
								<ref target="people.html#ShakespeareWilliam"
							>Shakespeare</ref>&apos;s <title><hi rendition="#italics"
								>Othello</hi></title>, respectively. </note></hi> and many other
					glorious shadows of the brain, possessed something more. However, the author of
						&apos;<title>Pride and Prejudice</title>,&apos; &amp;c., limited herself to
					this every-day world; and to return to the point of view in which her books
					yield moral benefit, we must think it a reader&apos;s own fault who does not
					close her pages with more charity in his heart towards unpretending, if prosing
					worth&#8212;with a higher estimation of simple kindness and sincere
					good-will&#8212;with a quickened sense of the duty of bearing and forbearing in
					domestic intercourse, and of the pleasure of adding to the little comforts even
					of persons who are neither wits nor beauties&#8212;who, in a word, does not feel
					more disposed to be benevolent. Miss Bates and her mother, Mrs. Jennings, old
					Mrs. Musgrave, all the foils who with half, or at most three quarters of an
					idea, are humble in their ignorance and happy in their simplicity&#8212;then the
					fools, who are only too life-like, from Mr. Rushworth and his &quot;forty-two
					speeches&quot; out of &apos;<title>Lovers Vows</title>,&apos; to Sir Walter Elliot, who hates
					the naval profession because it enables plebeians to fight their way to a title,
					and makes a man mahogany-colour before he is forty&#8212;then her worldly
					selfish people, who are delightful and benevolent everywhere but where it is
					their first duty, or at every one&apos;s expense but their own&#8212;Mrs.
					Elton&apos;s pretension, Aunt Norris&apos;s second-hand charity, all are
					inimitable. Characters of another grade, those very troublesome persons to draw,
					heroes and heroines, have in <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss
						Austen</ref>&apos;s pages spirit and reality. The hero is not a suit of
					fashionable clothes, and a set of fashionable phrases; the heroine is not a
					ball-dress, a fainting fit, and a volume of poetry; they too are taken from
					life, and are distinguished one from another. Caroline Morland, artless and
					sometimes a little awkward; Emma Woodhouse, clever, spoiled, candid, faulty, and
					yet delightful; Fanny Price, with her meekness and humility, her loving,
					loveable, and most forgiving temper, her weeping-willow spirit that principle
					strengthens into decision and self-dependence&#8212;none of these are alike, and
					none appeal to our good graces by virtue of any qualities that sisters and
					cousins in real life may not and do not possess. We sometimes feel that <ref
						target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>&apos;s works deal rather
					too largely with the commonplace, petty, and disagreeable side of human
					nature&#8212;that we should enjoy more frequent sketches of the wise and
					high-hearted&#8212;that some of the books are too completely pages out of the
					world. In the last posthumous tale (&apos;<title>Persuasion</title>&apos;) there
					is a strain of a higher mood; there is still the exquisite delineation of common
					life, such life as we hear, and see, and make part of, with the addition of a
					finer, more poetic, yet equally real tone of thought and action in the
					principals. <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref> was sparing
					in her introduction of nobler characters, for they are scattered sparingly in
					life, but the books in which she describes them most we like most; they may not
					amuse so much at the moment, but they interest more deeply and more happily. In
					many respects <ref target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref> resembled
						<ref target="people.html#CrabbeGeorge">Crabbe</ref>: she had not his genius
					for grappling with the passions, and forcing them to pass before the reader in
					living, suffering, bodily forms&#8212;but <ref target="people.html#CrabbeGeorge"
						>Crabbe</ref> in his lighter moods, unveiling the surface of things, playing
					with the follies of man, and even dealing seriously with such of his minor
					faults as all flesh is heir to. <ref target="people.html#CrabbeGeorge"
						>Crabbe</ref> himself, when not describing the terrible, is scarcely
					superior to the accomplished subject of this article. Her death has made a chasm
					in our light literature, the domestic novel with its home-borne incidents, its
					&quot;familiar matter of to-day,&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
								><ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam">Wordsworth</ref>,
							&quot;The Solitary Reaper&quot; 22.</note></hi> its slight array of
					names and great cognizance of people and things, its confinement to country
					life, and total oblivion of costume, manners, the<pb n="554"/> great world, and
					&quot;the mirror of fashion.&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
							>Published from 1798-1828, the popular <title><hi rendition="#italics"
									>Ladies&apos; Monthly Museum</hi></title> featured &quot;The
							Mirror of Fashion&quot; color plates of the latest clothing styles for
							women.</note></hi> Every species of composition, is, when good, to be
					admired in its way; but the revival of the domestic novel would make a pleasant
					interlude to the showy, sketchy, novels of high life. Hampshire (<ref
						target="people.html#AustenJane">Miss Austen</ref>&apos;s county) still
					possesses a female writer richly endowed with some of her predecessor&apos;s
					qualifications for this species of writing, and possessing on her own account a
					higher faculty of imagination. We allude to <ref
						target="people.html#SoutheyCaroline">Caroline Bowles</ref>.</p>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
