<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="PA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main" level="a">Review of Nouveaux Contes Moraux by Marmontel</title>
				<title type="subordinate" level="j">The Monthly Review</title>
				<author type="writer">
					<name>Elizabeth Moody</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
					<name xml:id="MW">Mary A. Waters</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>CoEditor</resp>
					<name xml:id="EW">Emma Wiley</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>MoodyRevNouveaux1801</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title type="main" level="a">Art. XVI. Nouveaux Contes Moraux, &amp;c. i.e.
							New Moral Tales. By Marmontel.</title>
						<author type="writer">Moody, Elizabeth (1737-1814)</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main" level="j">The Monthly Review</title>
						<imprint>
							<date when="1801-01">January-April 1801</date>
							<biblScope unit="vol">34</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page">542-44</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “, " for ”, '
						for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
					<p>Quotation marks that indicate block quotes have been silently eliminated.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
					<p>Compositors' catchwords and running titles have been silently eliminated.</p>
					<p>Long "s" (&#383;) has been silently modernized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>ARC Genre Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Advertisement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Animation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Catalog</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Chronology</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Essay</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Film, Documentary</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Film, Experimental</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Film, Narrative</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Film, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Historiography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Interview</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Liturgy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Musical Analysis</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Music, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Musical Work</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Musical Score</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Nonficition</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Performance</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Political Statement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g35">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g36">
						<catDesc>Scripture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g37">
						<catDesc>Sermon</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g38">
						<catDesc>Speech</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g39">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g40">
						<catDesc>Travel Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g41">
						<catDesc>Unspecified</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g42">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
					xml:id="f">
					<bibl>ARC Format Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="f1">
						<catDesc>Codex</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f2">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f3">
						<catDesc>Dataset</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f4">
						<catDesc>Drawing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f5">
						<catDesc>Illustration</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f6">
						<catDesc>Interactive Resource</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f7">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f8">
						<catDesc>Map</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f9">
						<catDesc>Moving Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f10">
						<catDesc>Notated Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f11">
						<catDesc>Page Proofs</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f12">
						<catDesc>Pamphlet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f13">
						<catDesc>Periodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f14">
						<catDesc>Physcial Object</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f15">
						<catDesc>Roll</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f16">
						<catDesc>Sheet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f17">
						<catDesc>Sound</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f18">
						<catDesc>Still Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f19">
						<catDesc>Typescript</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#lcsh">
					<list type="simple">
						<item>Criticism</item>
						<item>Book review</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="#g9 #g35" scheme="#g"/>
				<catRef target="#f13" scheme="#f"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#MW" when="2017-12-01" n="3">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>Encoding revision</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#EW" when="2017-03-09" n="2">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Emma Wiley</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#MW" when="2017-03-01" n="1">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>Created Edition</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head><bibl><lb rendition="#center"/><author type="writer"><ref
								target="people.html#MoodyElizabeth"><name>Elizabeth
								Moody</name></ref></author>
						<title type="main" level="a">
							<hi rendition="#smcaps">Art.</hi> XVI.<hi rendition="#italics"> Nouveaux
								Contes Moraux</hi>, &amp;c. <hi rendition="#italics">i.e.</hi> New
							Moral Tales. By <hi rendition="#smcaps"><ref
									target="people.html#Marmontel">Marmontel</ref>. 8vo.</hi> 4
							Vols. Paris. 1801. Imported by De Boffe, London, Price 18s. sewed.<hi
								rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">This review article appeared in
									the Foreign Appendix to <hi rendition="#italics"><title><ref
												target="people.html#ReviewMonthly">The Monthly
												Review</ref></title></hi>, Vol. 34 (January-April
									1801), pp. 542-544. The marked copy of the <hi
										rendition="#italics"><title><ref
												target="people.html#ReviewMonthly">Monthly
												Review</ref></title></hi> attributes this article to
									the collaborative efforts of <ref
										target="people.html#MoodyElizabeth"><name>Elizabeth
											Moody</name></ref> and her husband, <ref
										target="people.html#MoodyChristopherLake">Christopher Lake
										Moody</ref>. This edition of the article is produced by Emma
									Wiley and Mary A. Waters.</note></hi>
						</title></bibl></head>
				<p rendition="#pnoindent"><hi rendition="#largest">R</hi><hi rendition="#smcaps"
						>ecollecting</hi> the pleasure which we formerly received from the inventive
					genius and sprightly talents of the deceased author of these volumes, we took
					them up with an avidity and a confidence which precluded all idea of
					disappointment. If, said we to ourselves, these tales be genuine, (of which, we
					are told in the preface, the widow of <hi rendition="#smcaps"><ref
							target="people.html#Marmontel">Marmontel</ref></hi> has given the public
					an assurance,) we shall be much entertained: for, though the vigor of his mind
					may be in some degree abated, and the brilliancy of his setting may not
					altogether equal that of his meridian sun, yet <hi rendition="#smcaps"><ref
							target="people.html#Marmontel">Marmontel</ref></hi> must be <hi
						rendition="#smcaps"><ref target="people.html#Marmontel"
					>Marmontel</ref></hi>; and this new collection of Moral Tales must, by their
					prominent features, evince their affinity to those of which we gave an account
					in an early volume of our Review. (See M.R. vol. xxx. p. 59.) This consanguinity
					is proved indeed by indisputable marks; and, being the production of his graver
					years, these tales are more moral than those which were before published. If,
					also, they have lost some of the exuberance which distinguished the former, our
					opinion of them will shew that the merit of these is not lessened on that
					account.&#8212;The editor says that they will be found to possess equal merit
					with those tales which have given celebrity to the name of <hi
						rendition="#smcaps"><ref target="people.html#Marmontel"
					>Marmontel</ref></hi>; &#8212;that they display, in captivating language,
					invention, interest, ease, and elegance; that the moral which they inculcate is
					always amiable and pure; and in short that it has been the principal object of
					the author, to form the mind and taste of the rising generation, and to develop
					those germs of virtuous sentiments which nature has implanted in the human
					heart.&#8212;A publication of such a tendency, we can have no reluctance in
					recommending to the British public.</p>
				<p>The introductory tale is intitled <hi rendition="#italics">the Evening
						Meeting;</hi> and it describes a society of intimate friends, who, during
					the commotions of Paris, assembled at the country-house of a Madame <hi
						rendition="#italics">de Verval</hi>. As this lady was a great lover of
					stories, and possessed the talent of reciting them in the most natural and
					agreeable manner, she proposed that, for amusement, each of the party should in
					turn form and recount a tale, including the most interesting events of their
					life, without invading the sacred recesses of confidence. This proposition being
					accepted by the whole party, each narrates a personal memoir; and the general
					conclusion from the whole is that the parts of <milestone unit="signature"
						n="11" rendition="#center"/><pb n="543"/>our lives, which have contributed
					most to our happiness, are those which have originated in virtuous sentiments,
					or have been occupied in acts of benevolence.</p>
				<p> The second tale is called <hi rendition="#italics">the Tripod of <ref
							target="people.html#Helen">Helen</ref>;</hi> and its object seems to be
					to ridiculue the pride of philosophy, and to shew the limits of science. <hi
						rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#Marmontel"
						>Marmontel</ref></hi> might have taken these lines of Pope for his motto: <quote>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l>In parts superior what advantage lies?</l>
							<l>Say, for thou canst, what is it to be wise?</l>
							<l>&apos;Tis but to know how little can be known, </l>
							<l>To see all others&apos; faults and feel our own.<hi rendition="#sup"
										><note place="foot"><ref target="people.html#PopeAlexander"
											>Alexander Pope</ref>, <hi rendition="#italics"
												><title>Essay on Man</title></hi> (1733-4), Epistle
										IV, lines 259-62, slightly altered.</note></hi></l>
						</lg>
					</quote> This doctrine is illustrated with great vivacity of imagination, and
					excellent satire; and here we recognize the hand of <hi rendition="#smcaps"><ref
							target="people.html#Marmontel">Marmontel</ref></hi> himself. The scene
					is laid in remote antiquity. He supposes that <ref target="people.html#Helen"
						>Helen</ref> and Menelaus, being reconciled after the destruction of Troy,
					were returning to Laced&#230;mon, when they were assailed by a violent tempest
					as they were passing through the Cyclades, and were in imminent danger of being
					wrecked on the island of Cos. At this instant, <ref target="people.html#Helen"
						>Helen</ref> invoked the inconstant God of the ocean to protect a female
					whose disposition was so similar to his own; and, in order to give effect to her
					prayer, she presented him with a Golden Tripod, which had been saved from the
					pillage of Troy. On throwing this offering into the sea, the storm subsided, and
					the danger disappeared.&#8212;During six hundred years, this tripod lay at the
					bottom of the ocean: but at last it was again brought to light by some
					fishermen. After some contention about the property, between the neighbouring
					islands, it was wisely agreed to refer the matter to the decision of the Delphic
					Oracle; who settled the dispute by ordering the tripod to be presented to <hi
						rendition="#italics">the Wisest of the Wise</hi>. Where however, were they
					to find this distinguished personage? They were puzzled to ascertain to which of
					the seven wise men, who flourished in Greece at that period, this title
					belonged: but, apprehending that this was a question which the philosophers
					themselves could easily determine, they appoint deputies to wait on them
					respectively; who commence with an application to <hi rendition="#italics"
						>Thales</hi>, the Milesian, their neighbour.</p>
				<p>This philosopher, however, fairly confesses that all his knowledge has only
					served to convince him <hi rendition="#italics">how little he knows</hi>; and
					that he continues his researches only with the view of encouraging his
					disciples, and in the hope that time, in his wonder-working progress, may lift
					up some corner of the immense veil of nature. He therefore advises them to offer
					the tripod to <hi rendition="#italics">Solon</hi>, who pursues the straight path
					to usefulness in the study of man, and whose object is to render him better and
					happier.&#8212;In consequence, the deputies next apply to the Athenian
					legislator, but with no better success. <hi rendition="#italics">Solon</hi>
					re-<pb n="544"/>fers them to <hi rendition="#italics">Bias, Bias</hi> to <hi
						rendition="#italics">Chilo</hi> the Spartan, &amp;c. and thus the tripod is
					bandied about from sage to sage; each of whom, acknowledging his own
					insufficiency and weakness, rejects the epithet of <hi rendition="#italics">the
						Wisest of the Wise</hi>. In this conduct, perhaps, they are represented as
					much wiser than they really were; for here it appears that they <hi
						rendition="#italics">knew themselves</hi>, which is one of the most
					difficult attainments. The seven wise men of Greece, each rejecting for himself
					the high compliment of <hi rendition="#italics">the Wisest of the Wise</hi>,
					agree to give their several definitions of wisdom; and to award the tripod to
					him who should unite its characters in the highest degree. One defines it to
					consist in an <hi rendition="#italics">unalterable tranquillity of mind, under
						all the diversities of fortune;</hi> another, in <hi rendition="#italics">a
						profound self knowledge, applied in rendering ourselves good and happy;</hi>
					a third, <hi rendition="#italics">in the moderation of our desires;</hi> the
					fourth, in the <hi rendition="#italics">power of regulating the present, and
						preparing for the future, by the experience of the past;</hi> another, <hi
						rendition="#italics">in a strength of mind which is capable of resisting the
						passions;</hi> and the sixth, <hi rendition="#italics">in the absolute
						empire of reason over the will</hi>.&#8212; Scarcely are these definitions
					of wisdom given, when <hi rendition="#italics">Bias</hi> concludes by deciding
					that these attributes can never unite in any individual mortal, and that they
					can belong only to a God. Hence, it is decreed that the Golden Tripod should be
					carried to the temple at Delphos, and there consecrated to <ref
						target="people.html#Apollo">Apollo</ref>. </p>
				<p>Having but lately received these volumes, and having now approached to the close
					of our present Appendix, we cannot enter into an analysis of the other tales
					which they contain: but we shall subjoin the titles of them, in order to give
					our readers some idea of their nature and subjects. III. <hi
						rendition="#italics">The Lesson of Misfortune</hi>. IV. <hi
						rendition="#italics">The School of Friendship:</hi> in which we have a tutor
					resembling <ref target="people.html#SirCharlesGrandison">Sir Charles
						Grandison</ref>, and a pupil not unlike <ref
						target="people.html#EmilyJervois">Emily Jervis</ref>, innocently in love
					with him. V. <hi rendition="#italics">The Generous Breton</hi>. VI. <hi
						rendition="#italics">The Error of a good Father</hi>. This tale was related
					by <hi rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#Cideville"
						>Cideville</ref></hi> to <hi rendition="#italics"><ref
							target="people.html#Voltaire">Voltaire</ref></hi> when he was
					ill:&#8212;the descriptions in it are beautifully pathetic. VII. <hi
						rendition="#italics">The Casket</hi>. VIII. <hi rendition="#italics">The
						Self-Rivals</hi>. IX. <hi rendition="#italics">The Villages Breakfasts</hi>.
					X. <hi rendition="#italics">The Watermen of Besons</hi>. XI. <hi
						rendition="#italics">It must be so</hi>. <hi rendition="#smcaps">XII</hi>.
						<hi rendition="#italics">The Hermits of Murica</hi>. XIII. <hi
						rendition="#italics">Palemon</hi>, an Arcadian Pastoral, from two pictures
					by <hi rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#Poussin"
					>Poussin</ref></hi>. XIV. <hi rendition="#italics">Fire-side-recollection</hi>.
					XV. <hi rendition="#italics">The Mountain of the two Lovers.</hi></p>
				<p>Some of these tales were printed in the <hi rendition="#italics"
							><title>Mercure</title></hi><hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">The
							French literary journal <hi rendition="#italics"><title>Mercure de
									France</title></hi> was published with some interruptions from
							1672-1825.</note></hi> in the years 1789, 90, 91, and 92. They abound
					with genuine satire and wit, with pathetic sentiment and sound sense. </p>
				<p>Prefixed to the 1st vol. is a portrait of the author; under which is a memorandum
					that <hi rendition="#smcaps"><ref target="people.html#Marmontel">Jean-Francois
							Marmontel</ref></hi> was born on the 11th of July 1723, and died at
					Abbeville, Dec 29, 1799.</p>

			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
