<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="PA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main" level="a">On the Ancient and Modern Influence Of Poetry.</title>
				<title type="subordinate" level="j">New Monthly Magazine and Literary
					Journal</title>
				<author type="writer">
					<name>Letitia Landon</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>General Editor</resp>
					<name xml:id="MW">Mary A. Waters</name>
				</respStmt>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Editing and encoding assistance</resp>
					<name xml:id="VS">Victoria Stewart</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>LandonPoetry1832</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title type="main" level="a">On the Ancient and Modern Influence of
							Poetry.</title>
						<author type="writer">L. E. L. (Letitia Elizabeth Landon),
							1802-1838</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main" level="j">New Monthly Magazine and Literary
							Journal</title>
						<imprint>
							<date when="1804-12">November 1832</date>
							<biblScope unit="vol">35</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="no"/>
							<biblScope unit="page">466-71</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “, " for ”, '
						for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
					<p>Quotation marks that indicate block quotes have been silently eliminated.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as&#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
					<p>Compositors' catchwords and running titles have been silently eliminated.</p>
					<p>Long "s" (&#383;) has been silently modernized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>ARC Genre Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Advertisement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Animation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Catalog</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Chronology</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Essay</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Film, Documentary</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Film, Experimental</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Film, Narrative</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Film, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Historiography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Interview</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Liturgy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Musical Analysis</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Music, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Musical Work</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Musical Score</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Nonficition</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Performance</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Political Statement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g35">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g36">
						<catDesc>Scripture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g37">
						<catDesc>Sermon</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g38">
						<catDesc>Speech</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g39">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g40">
						<catDesc>Travel Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g41">
						<catDesc>Unspecified</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g42">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E"
					xml:id="f">
					<bibl>ARC Format Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="f1">
						<catDesc>Codex</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f2">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f3">
						<catDesc>Dataset</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f4">
						<catDesc>Drawing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f5">
						<catDesc>Illustration</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f6">
						<catDesc>Interactive Resource</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f7">
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f8">
						<catDesc>Map</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f9">
						<catDesc>Moving Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f10">
						<catDesc>Notated Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f11">
						<catDesc>Page Proofs</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f12">
						<catDesc>Pamphlet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f13">
						<catDesc>Periodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f14">
						<catDesc>Physcial Object</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f15">
						<catDesc>Roll</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f16">
						<catDesc>Sheet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f17">
						<catDesc>Sound</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f18">
						<catDesc>Still Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="f19">
						<catDesc>Typescript</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#lcsh">
					<list type="simple">
						<item>Criticism</item>
						<item>Essay</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="#g9 #g12" scheme="#g"/>
				<catRef target="#f13" scheme="#f"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#MW" when="2018-07-15" n="3">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>revise TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#VS" when="2017-02-11" n="2">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Victoria Stewart</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#MW" when="2016-12-01" n="1">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>Created Edition</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head><bibl><lb rendition="#center"/><author type="writer"><ref
								target="people.html#LandonLetitia"><name>Letitia
							Landon</name></ref></author>
						<title type="main" level="a">ON THE ANCIENT AND MODERN INFLUENCE OF
								POETRY.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><title level="j"><hi
											rendition="#italics">New Monthly Magazine and Literary
											Journal</hi></title> (2nd series) no. 35 (November
									1832): 466-71. Victoria Stewart and Mary A. Waters
									co-edited this edition for <hi rendition="#italics">The Criticism
										Archive</hi>.</note></hi></title></bibl></head>
				<p><hi rendition="#largest">I</hi><hi rendition="#smcaps">t</hi> is curious to
					observe how little one period resembles another. Centuries are the children of
					one mighty family, but there is no family-likeness between them. We ourselves
					are standing on the threshold of a new era, and we are already hastening to make
					as wide a space, mark as vast a difference as possible, between our own age and
					its predecessor. Whatever follies we may go back upon, whatever opinions we may
					re-adopt, they are never those which have gone <hi rendition="#italics"
						>immediately</hi> before us. Already there is a wide gulph between the last
					century and the present. In religion, in philosophy, in politics, in manners,
					there has passed a great change; but in none has been worked a greater change
					than in poetry, whether as it regards the art itself, or the general feeling
					towards it. The decline and fall of that Roman empire of the mind seems now
					advanced as an historical fact; while we are equally ready to admit that some
					twenty years since the republic was in its plenitude of power. In the meantime a
					new set of aspirants have arisen, and a new set of opinions are to be won. But
					it is from the past that we best judge of the present; and perhaps we shall more
					accurately say what poetry is by referring to what it has been.</p>
				<p>Poetry in every country has had its origin in three sources, connected with the
					strongest feelings belonging to the human mind&#8212;Religion, War, and Love.
					The mysteries of the present; the still greater mysteries of the future; the
					confession of some superior power so deeply felt; higher impulses speaking so
					strongly of some spiritual influence of a purer order than those of our common
					wants and wishes;&#8212;these all found words and existence in poetry. The
					vainest fictions of mythology were the strongest possible evidence how necessary
					to the ignorance of humanity was the belief of a superior power; so entire was
					the interior conviction, that sooner than believe in nothing no belief was too
					absurd for adoption. The imagination, which is the source of poetry, has in
					every country been the beginning as well as the ornament of civilization. It
					civilizes because it refines. A general view of its influence in the various
					quarters of the globe will place this in the most striking point of view.</p>
				<p>Africa is the least civilized quarter of the globe, not so much from its savage
					as from its apathetic state; one could almost believe that it had been formed
					from the dregs of the other parts. Now, the distinguishing mark of its
					deficiency in that soil of mind wherewith the intellect works, is its total want
					of imagination. It is the only great portion of the world which is not
					emphatically made known to us by its own peculiar religion. Her mythology was
					the earthly immortality of Greece. Greece is indelibly linked with the idea of
					civilization; but all those fine and graceful beliefs which made its springs
					holy places, and haunted the fragrant life of every flower and leaf, were the
					creations of earliest time. Look from thence to the fierce regions of the
					North,&#8212;how full is the Scandinavian faith of the wild and wonderful! or to
					the East, how gorgeous their tales of enchantment, with their delicate Peris,<hi
						rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">Supernatural beings of Persian mythology
							endowed with grace and beauty.</note></hi> and the fallen and fearful
					spirits in their subterranean caverns!&#8212;again, the faith of Brahma, with
					its thousand deities. Or, to cross the wide Atlantic, there are the vestiges of
					a terrible creed yet<pb n="467"/>touched with something of spiritual loveliness,
					in their singing-birds bringing tidings of the departed, and in the green
					hunting-grounds which made their future hope. Each and all these creeds are the
					work and wonder of the imagination&#8212;but in these Africa has no part. No
					august belief fills with beauty or terror the depths of her forests, and no
					fallen temple makes its site sacred though in ruins. Her creeds have neither
					beauty nor grandeur. The Devil is their principal Deity, and their devotion is
					born of physical fear. Other nations have had their various faiths, created and
					coloured by the scenes which gave them birth. The religion of Greece was
					beautiful as her own myrtle and olive groves. The Scandinavian was like its own
					wild mountains and snowy wastes, with just gleams of beauty from its starry
					nights and meteors. The Arabian was glowing and magnificent as the summer earth
					and radiant sky of its believers; while that of the American Indian was terrible
					as the huge serpents and the interminable forests which gave shelter to its
					mysteries. But in Africa the sunny sky, the noble rivers, the woods, splendid in
					size and foliage, have been without their wonted effect. Slaves from the
					earliest period, the very superstitions of her sable sons are mean fears caught
					from their masters; all about them is earthly, utterly unredeemed by those
					spiritual awakenings which are as lights from another world. We might believe
					that some great original curse has been said over them, and that they are given
					over into the hand of man and not of God. And in simple truth that curse has
					been slavery. The Helots<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">Serfs of ancient
							Sparta.</note></hi> even of Greece were uninspired. &quot;A slave cannot
					be eloquent,&quot; said <ref target="people.html#Longinus"
						><name>Longinus</name></ref><hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
								target="people.html#LandonLetitia"><name>Landon</name></ref>
							probably relies on her memory of Section XLIV of William Smith&apos;s
							1739 translation of <ref target="people.html#Longinus"
									><name>Longinus</name></ref>&apos;s <hi rendition="#italics"
									><title>On the Sublime</title></hi>, &quot;but never yet did a
							slave become an orator.&quot; Smith&apos;s rendering established the
							text for English audiences and was frequently reprinted into the
							nineteenth century.</note></hi>; nor poetical either&#8212;the wells of
					his enthusiasm are dried up. What some ancient writer says of iron may be
					applied to Poetry&#8212;its use is the first step to civilization, and
					civilization is freedom.</p>

				<p>Next to Religion War was the great source of poetry; and the deeds of the brave
					were sung in that spirit of encouragement which one man will ever receive from
					the praise bestowed on the deeds of another, when he meditates similar
					achievements of his own. And here we may be permitted a few words on what we
					cannot but consider an unjust and erroneous opinion, now much insisted
					upon,&#8212;that poets and conquerors have been equal enemies of the human
					race&#8212;the one but acting what the other praised; and that the sin of
					encouragement was equal, if not greater, than that of commission. In answer to
					this we must observe that it is not fair to judge of former actions by our
					present standard. Our first view of society is always the same: we see the human
					race dwelling in small dispersed sets, with rude habits, the results of
					hardships and of dangers. A more favourable situation, or, more commonly, the
					influence of some superior mind, which from the wonderful effects produced by a
					single man is often a nation&apos;s history: these or similar causes first
					placed some of the tribes in positions of comparative comfort and advancement.
					This position would of course be envied by their savage and starving neighbours,
					who would consider brute force the only means of sharing their advantages.
					Single motives never last: ambition, aggrandisement, conquest with a view to
					security, soon gave a thousand motives to warfare that had originally began in
					want and self-defence. It has required centuries so to consolidate kingdoms that
					now a breathing space is allowed for reflection on the sin of sacrificing
					man&apos;s most valuable possession&#8212;life. But what part has the poet taken
					in these scenes of bloodshed? One certainly of amelioration. If he has sung of
						con-<milestone unit="signature" n="2 H 2" rendition="#center"/><pb n="468"
					/>querors, the qualities held up to admiration were those of magnanimity and
					generosity. He has spoken of the love of liberty as holding light the love of
					life; and the highest eulogium of a warrior was that he died in defence of his
					native country. But to give our assertion the support of an
					example&#8212;Perhaps the spirit which animates, the desire which excites, the
					power which supports, a conqueror, were never more entirely personified than in
						<ref target="people.html#Xerxes">Xerxes</ref>. He possessed to the utmost
					that grasping ambition, that carelessness of human blood, which characterize the
					mere conqueror; yet with all the purple pomp of his power, we are not aware of
					his having been held up otherwise than in reprobation, while the whole world has
					been filled with the fame of his brave opposers; and the names of those who fell
					at Marathon are still the watchwords of freedom. Again, in the days of chivalry,
					what were the qualities the minstrel lauded in the knight?&#8212;his valour,
					certainly, but still more his courtesy, his protection of the weak against the
					strong, his devotion, his truth;&#8212;till the &quot;ungentle knight&quot; was
					almost as much a phrase of disgrace as that of the &quot;recreant.&quot;</p>

				<p>Love was the third great fountain of poetry&apos;s inspiration; and who that has
					ever loved will deny the necessity of a language, beyond the working-day tongue
					of our ordinary run of hopes and fears, to express feelings which have so little
					in common with them. What has been the most popular love-poetry in all
					countries?&#8212;that which gave expression to its spiritual and better
					part&#8212;constancy kept like a holy thing&#8212;blessings on the beloved one,
					though in that blessing we have ourselves no share; or sad and affectionate
					regrets in whose communion our own nature grows more kindly from its sympathy.
					We are always the better for entering into other’s sorrow or other&apos;s
					joy.</p>

				<p>The whole origin and use of poetry may be expressed in a few brief words: it
					originates in that idea of superior beauty and excellence inherent in every
					nature&#8212;and it is employed to keep that idea alive; and the very belief in
					excellence is one cause of its existence. When we speak of poetry as the
					fountain whence youth draws enthusiasm for its hopes,&#8212;where the warrior
					strengthens his courage, and the lover his faith,&#8212;the treasury where the
					noblest thoughts are garnered,&#8212;the archives where the noblest deeds are
					recorded,&#8212;we but express an old belief. One of our great reviews&#8212;the
						&quot;<ref target="people.html#WestminsterReview"
						><title>Westminster</title></ref>&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"/>&#8212;in
					speaking of the fine arts, &amp;c. says, &quot;The aristocracy do well to
					encourage poetry: it is by fiction themselves exist&#8212;and what is poetry but
						fiction?&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">Not
						identified.</note></hi> fiction; its merit and its power lie alike in its
					truth: to one heart the aspiring and elevated will come home; to another the
					simple and natural: the keynote to one will be the voice of memory, which brings
					back young affections&#8212;early confidence,&#8212;hill and valley yet glad
					with the buoyant step which once past over them,&#8212;flowers thrice lovely
					from thoughts indelibly associated with their leaf or breath: such as these are
					touched by all that restores, while it recalls, days whose enjoyment would have
					been happiness, could they but have had the knowledge of experience without its
					weariness. To another, poetry will be a vision and a delight, because the virtue
					of which he dreams is there realized&#8212;and because the &quot;love which his
					spirit has painted&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
								target="people.html#ByronGeorge"
							><name>Byron</name></ref>,&quot;Stanzas to [Augusta]&quot;
						7.</note></hi> is to be found in its pages. But in each and all cases the
					deep well of sympathy is only to be found when the hazel rod is poised by the
					hand of truth. And, till some moral steam is discovered as potent as that now so
					active in the physical<pb n="469"/>world, vain will be the effort to regulate
					mankind like machinery: there will ever be spiritual awakenings, and deep and
					tender thoughts, to turn away from the hurry and highways of life, and whose
					place of refuge will still be the green paths and pleasant waters of poesy. That
					tribes of worse than idle followers have crowded the temple, and cast the dust
					they brought around the soiled altar,&#8212;that many have profaned their high
					gift to base use&#8212;that poetry has often turned aside from its divine origin
					and diviner end,&#8212;is what must be equally admitted and lamented; but who
					will deny that our best and most popular (indeed in this case best and popular
					are equivalent terms) poetry makes its appeal to the higher and better feelings
					of our nature, and not a poet but owes his fame to that which best deserves it?
					What a code of pure and beautiful morality, applicable to almost every
					circumstance, might be drawn from <ref target="people.html#ShakespeareWilliam"
							><name>Shakspeare</name></ref>!</p>

				<p>The influence of poetry has two eras,&#8212;first as it tends to civilize;
					secondly as it tends to prevent that very civilization from growing too cold and
					too selfish. Its first is its period of action; its second is that of feeling
					and reflection: it is that second period which at present exists. On the mere
					principle of utility, in our wide and weary world, with its many sorrows and
					more cares, how anxiously we ought to keep open every source of happiness! and
					who among us does not recollect some hour when a favourite poet spread before us
					a page like that of a magician&apos;s; when some expression has seemed like the
					very echo of our feelings; how often and with what a sensation of pleasure have
					long-remembered passages sprang to our lips; how every natural beauty has caught
					a fresh charm from being linked with some associate verse! Who that has these or
					similar recollections but would keep the ear open, and the heart alive, to the
					&quot;song that lightens the languid way!&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot"><ref target="people.html#MooreThomas"><name>Sir Thomas
									Moore&apos;s</name></ref> &quot;Boat Glee,&quot; a ballad from
							the comic opera <hi rendition="#italics">M. P., or The Blue
								Stocking</hi> (1811).</note></hi></p>

				<p>Why one age should be more productive in poetry than another is one of those
					questions&#8212;a calculation of the mental longitude&#8212;likely to remain
					unanswered. That peculiar circumstances do not create the poet is proved by the
					fact, that only one individual is so affected: if it were mere circumstance, it
					would affect alike all who are brought within its contact. What confirmation of
					this theory (if theory it be) is to be found in the history of all
					poets!&#8212;where are we to seek the cause which made them such, if not in
					their own minds? We daily see men living amid beautiful scenery; and scenery is
					much dwelt upon the advocates of circumstance. Switzerland is a most beautiful
					country, yet what great poet has it ever produced? The spirit which in ancient
					days peopled grove and mountain with Dryad and Oread,<hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot"> Nymphs from classical mythology.</note></hi> or, in modern
					times, with associations, must be in him who sees, not in the object seen. How
					many there are, leading a life of literary leisure, living in a romantic
					country, and writing poetry all their days, who yet go down to their
					unremembered graves no more poets than if they had never turned a stanza! While,
					on the other hand, we see men with every obstacle before them, with little
					leisure and less encouragement, yet force their upward way, make their voice
					heard, and leave their memory in imperishable song. Take <ref
						target="people.html#BurnsRobert"><name>Burns</name></ref> for an example:
					much stress has been laid on the legendary ballads he was accustomed to hear
					from infancy; but if these were so potent, why did they not inspire his brother
					as well as himself? <ref target="people.html#BurnsGilbert"><name>Mr. Gilbert
							Burns</name></ref> is recorded, by every biographer, to have been a
					sensible, and even a superior man; he dwelt in the same country&#8212;he heard
					the same songs&#8212;why was he not a poet too? There can be but one<pb n="470"
					/> answer,&#8212;there was not that inherent quality in his mind which there was
					in his brother&apos;s. Many young men are born to a higher name than
					fortune&#8212;many spend their youth amid the most exciting scenes&#8212;yet why
					do none of these turn out a <ref target="people.html#ByronGeorge"
							><name>Byron</name></ref>, but for some innate first cause? What made
						<ref target="people.html#MiltonJohn"><name>Milton</name></ref> in old
					age,&#8212;in sickness, in poverty&#8212;depressed by all that would have
					weighed to the very dust an ordinary man&#8212;without one of man&apos;s
					ordinary encouragements,&#8212;what could have made him turn to the future as to
					a home, collect his glorious energies, and finish a work, the noblest aid ever
					given to the immortality of a language? What, but that indefinable spirit, whose
					enthusiasm is nature&apos;s own gift to the poet. <hi rendition="#italics">Poeta
						nascitur non fit</hi><hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"> The poet is
							born, not made.</note></hi> is, like many other old truths, the very
					truth after all.</p>

				<p>We cannot but consider that, though some be still among us, our own great poets
					belong to another age. Their fame is established, and their horde of imitators
					have dispersed; those wearying followers who, to use the happy expression of a
					contemporary writer, &quot;think that breaking the string is bending the bow of
						<ref target="people.html#Ulysses"><name>Ulysses</name></ref>.&quot; We hear
					daily complaints of the want of present taste and talent for poetry: we are more
					prepared to admit the latter than the former. In the most sterile times of the
					imagination, love of poetry has never been lacking; the taste may have been bad,
					but still the taste existed. <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"
							><name>Wordsworth</name></ref> truly says, &quot;that, with the young,
					poetry is a passion;&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"> Essay,
							&quot;Supplementary to the Preface&quot; to <hi rendition="#italics"
								>Lyrical Ballads.</hi> (1815) </note></hi> and there will always be
					youth in the world to indulge the hopes, and feel the warm and fresh emotions,
					which their fathers have found to be vain, or have utterly exhausted. To these,
					poetry will ever be a natural language; and it is the young who make the
					reputation of a poet. We soon lose that keen delight, which marvels if others
					share not in it: the faculty of appreciation is the first which leaves us. It is
					tact rather than feeling which enables experience to foresee the popularity of a
					new poet. As to the alleged want of taste, we only refer to the editions of
					established authors which still find purchasers: one has just appeared of <ref
						target="people.html#ScottWalter"><name>Scott</name></ref>, another of <ref
						target="people.html#ByronGeorge"><name>Byron</name></ref>. With what
					enthusiasm do some set up <ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"
							><name>Wordsworth</name></ref> for an idol, and others <ref
						target="people.html#ShelleyPercy"><name>Shelley</name></ref>! But this taste
					is quite another feeling to that which creates; and the little now written
					possesses beauty not originality. The writers do not set their own mark on their
					property: one might have put forth the work of the other, or it might be that of
					their predecessors. This was not the case some few years ago. Who could have
					mistaken the picturesque and chivalric pages of <ref
						target="people.html#ScottWalter"><name>Scott</name></ref> for the
					impassioned one of <ref target="people.html#ByronGeorge"
						><name>Byron</name></ref>? or who could for a moment have hesitated as to
					whether a poem was marked with the actual and benevolent philosophy of <ref
						target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"><name>Wordsworth</name></ref>, or the
					beautiful but ideal theory of <ref target="people.html#ShelleyPercy"
							><name>Shelley</name></ref>? We are now producing no great or original
					(the words are synonymous) poet. We have graceful singing in the bower, but no
					voice that startles us into wonder, and hurries us forth to see whose trumpet is
					awakening the land. We know that when the snow has long lain, warming and
					fertilizing the ground, and when the late summer comes, hot and clear, the rich
					harvest will be abundant under such genial influences. Perhaps poetry too may
					have its atmosphere; and a long cold winter may be needed for its glad and
					glorious summer. The soil of song, like that of earth, may need rest for
					renewal. Again we repeat, that though the taste be not, the spirit of the day
					is, adverse to the production of poetry. Selfishness is its principle,
					indifference its affectation, and ridicule its commonplace. We allow no appeals
					save to our reason, or to our fear <pb n="471"/> of laughter. We must either be
					convinced or sneered into things. Neither calculation nor sarcasm are the
					elements for poetry. A remark made by <ref target="people.html#ScottWalter"
							><name>Scott</name></ref> to one of his great compeers shows how he knew
					the age in which he was fated to end his glorious
					career:&#8212;&quot;Ah&#8212;it is well that we have made our reputation!&quot;
					The personal is the destroyer of the spiritual; and to the former everything is
					now referred. We talk of the author&apos;s self more than his works, and we know
					his name rather than his writings. There is a base macadamizing spirit in
					literature; we seek to level all the high places of old. But till we can deny
					that fine &quot;farther looking hope&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot">
							<ref target="people.html#WordsworthWilliam"
								><name>Wordsworth</name></ref>, &quot;The Force of Prayer, or, The
							Founding of Boulton Priory, A Tradition&quot; 47. </note></hi> which
					gives such a charm to <ref target="people.html#ShakespeareWilliam"
							><name>Shakespeare&apos;s</name></ref> confessional sonnets; till we can
					deny that &quot;<title>The Paradise Lost</title>&quot; was the work of old age,
					poverty, and neglect, roused into delightful exertion by a bright futurity; till
					we can deny the existence of those redeemers of humanity&#8212;we must admit,
					also, the existence of a higher, more prophetic, more devoted and self-relying
					spirit than is to be accounted for on the principles either of vanity or of
					lucre: we shall be compelled to admit that its inspiration is, indeed, <quote>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l>A heavenly breath</l>
							<l>Along an earthly lyre.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
											target="people.html#BlanchardLaman"><name>Laman
												Blanchard</name></ref>, &quot;The Spirit of
										Poesy&quot; 5-6.</note></hi></l>
						</lg></quote></p>
				<p>Methinks there are some mysteries in the soul on whose precincts it were well to
					&quot;tread with unsandalled foot.&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
							>An untraced but commonly repeated poetic phrase.</note></hi> Poetry
					like religion requires faith, and we are the better and happier for yielding it.
					The imagination is to the mind what life is to the body&#8212;its vivifying and
					active part. In antiquity, poetry had to create, it now has to preserve. Its
					first effort was against barbarism, its last is against selfishness. A world of
					generous emotions, of kindly awakenings, those <quote>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l>Which bid the perished pleasures move</l>
							<l>In mournful mockery o&apos;er the soul of love;<hi rendition="#sup"
										><note place="foot"><ref
											target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuel">Samuel Taylor Coleridge</ref>,
										&quot;Lines On an Autumnal Evening&quot;
								7-8.</note></hi></l>
						</lg></quote> a world of thought and feeling, now lies in the guardianship
					of the poet. These are they who sit in the gate called the beautiful, which
					leads to the temple. Its meanest priests should feel that their office is
					sacred. Enthusiasm is no passion of the drawing-room, or of the pence-table: its
					home is the heart, and its hope is afar. This is too little the creed of our
					generation; yet, without such creed, poetry has neither present life nor future
					immortality. As <ref target="people.html#WhiteheadCharles"
							><name>Whitehead</name></ref> finely says in his poem of &quot;The Solitary,&quot;&#8212;<quote>
						<lg type="stanza">
							<l rendition="#indent1">Not for herself, not for the wealth she
								brings,</l>
							<l>Is the muse wooed and won, but for the deep,</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">Occult, profound, unfathomabl things,&#8212;</l>
							<l>The engine of our tears whene&apos;er we weep,</l>
							<l>The impulse of our dreams when&apos;er we sleep,</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">The mysteries that our sad hearts possess,</l>
							<l>Which, and the keys whereof, the Muse doth keep,&#8212;</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">Oh ! to kindle soft humanity, to raise,</l>
							<l>With gentle strength infused, the spirit bowed;</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">To pour a second sunlight on our days,</l>
							<l>And draw the restless lightining from our cloud;</l>
							<l>To cheer the humble and to dash the proud.</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">Besought in peace to live, in peace to
								die,&#8212;</l>
							<l rendition="#indent1">The poet&apos;s task is done&#8212;Oh,
								Immortality! <hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
											target="people.html#WhiteheadCharles"><name>Charles
												Whitehead</name></ref> (1804-1862), <hi
											rendition="#italics">The Solitary</hi>
									397-414.</note></hi></l>
						</lg></quote> He is only a true poet, who can say, in the words of <ref
						target="people.html#ColeridgeSamuel"><name>Coledridge</name></ref>, &quot;My
					task has been my delight; I have not looked either to guerdon or praise, and to
					me Poetry is its own exceeding great reward.&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot">Preface to <hi rendition="#italics">The Poetical Works of
								S. T. Coleridge</hi> (London: William Pickering, 1828).</note></hi>
				</p>


			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
