<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="PA.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title type="main" level="a">&quot;On Novel Writing&quot;</title>
				<title type="subordinate" level="j">The Literary Magazine and American
					Register</title>
				<author type="writer">
					<name>Anna Letitia Barbauld</name>
				</author>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Editor</resp>
					<name xml:id="MW">Mary A. Waters</name>
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<idno>NovelWritingBar1804</idno>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title type="main" level="a">On Novel Writing</title>
						<author type="writer"><name>Barbauld, Mrs. (Anna Letitia), 1743-1825</name></author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title type="main" level="j">The Literary Magazine and American
							Register</title>
						<imprint>
							<date when="1804-12">December 1804</date>
							<biblScope unit="vol">2</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="no">15</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page">693-98</biblScope>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation>
					<p>All quotation marks and apostrophes have been changed: " for “, " for ”, '
						for ‘, and ' for ’.</p>
					<p>Quotation marks that indicate block quotes have been silently eliminated.</p>
				</quotation>
				<hyphenation eol="none">
					<p>Any dashes occurring in line breaks have been removed.</p>
					<p>Because of web browser variability, all hyphens have been typed on the U.S.
						keyboard</p>
					<p>Em-dashes have been rendered as &#8212;</p>
				</hyphenation>
				<normalization method="markup">
					<p>Spelling has not been regularized.</p>
					<p>Writing in other hands appearing on these manuscripts has been indicated as
						such, the content recorded in brackets.</p>
					<p>Compositors' catchwords and running titles have been silently eliminated.</p>
					<p>Long "s" (&#383;) has been silently modernized.</p>
				</normalization>
				<normalization>
					<p>&amp; has been used for the ampersand sign.</p>
					<p>£ has been used for £, the pound sign</p>
					<p>All other characters, those with accents, non-breaking spaces, etc., have
						been encoded in HTML entity decimals.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
			<classDecl>
				<taxonomy
					corresp="http://www.performantsoftware.com/nines_wiki/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cnines:genre.3E"
					xml:id="g">
					<bibl>ARC Genre Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id="g1">
						<catDesc>Advertisement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g2">
						<catDesc>Animation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g3">
						<catDesc>Bibliography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g4">
						<catDesc>Catalog</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g5">
						<catDesc>Chronology</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g7">
						<catDesc>Citation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g6">
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g8">
						<catDesc>Correspondence</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g9">
						<catDesc>Criticism</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g10">
						<catDesc>Drama</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g11">
						<catDesc>Ephemera</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g12">
						<catDesc>Essay</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g13">
						<catDesc>Fiction</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g14">
						<catDesc>Film, Documentary</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g15">
						<catDesc>Film, Experimental</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g16">
						<catDesc>Film, Narrative</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g17">
						<catDesc>Film, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g18">
						<catDesc>Historiography</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g19">
						<catDesc>Interview</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g20">
						<catDesc>Life Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g21">
						<catDesc>Liturgy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g22">
						<catDesc>Musical Analysis</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g23">
						<catDesc>Music, Other</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g24">
						<catDesc>Musical Work</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g25">
						<catDesc>Musical Score</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g26">
						<catDesc>Nonficition</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g27">
						<catDesc>Paratext</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g28">
						<catDesc>Performance</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g29">
						<catDesc>Philosophy</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g30">
						<catDesc>Photograph</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g31">
						<catDesc>Political Statement</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g32">
						<catDesc>Poetry</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g33">
						<catDesc>Religion</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g34">
						<catDesc>Reference Works</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g35">
						<catDesc>Review</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g36">
						<catDesc>Scripture</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g37">
						<catDesc>Sermon</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g38">
						<catDesc>Speech</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g39">
						<catDesc>Translation</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g40">
						<catDesc>Travel Writing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g41">
						<catDesc>Unspecified</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id="g42">
						<catDesc>Visual Art</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
				<taxonomy corresp="http://wiki.collex.org/index.php/Submitting_RDF#.3Cdc:type.3E" xml:id="f">
					<bibl>ARC Format Categories, July 1, 2017</bibl>
					<category xml:id='f1'>
						<catDesc>Codex</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f2'>
						<catDesc>Collection</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f3'>
						<catDesc>Dataset</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f4'>
						<catDesc>Drawing</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f5'>
						<catDesc>Illustration</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f6'>
						<catDesc>Interactive Resource</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f7'>
						<catDesc>Manuscript</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f8'>
						<catDesc>Map</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f9'>
						<catDesc>Moving Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f10'>
						<catDesc>Notated Music</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f11'>
						<catDesc>Page Proofs</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f12'>
						<catDesc>Pamphlet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f13'>
						<catDesc>Periodical</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f14'>
						<catDesc>Physcial Object</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f15'>
						<catDesc>Roll</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f16'>
						<catDesc>Sheet</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f17'>
						<catDesc>Sound</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f18'>
						<catDesc>Still Image</catDesc>
					</category>
					<category xml:id='f19'>
						<catDesc>Typescript</catDesc>
					</category>
				</taxonomy>
			</classDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords scheme="#lcsh">
					<list type="simple">
						<item>English literature</item>
						<item>History</item>
					</list>
				</keywords>
				<catRef target="#g9 #g12" scheme="#g"/>
				<catRef target="#f13" scheme="#f"/>
			</textClass>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="#MW" when="2016-07-15" n="3">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>revise TEI encoding</item>
					<item>document ID change</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change  who="#MW" when="2010-12-01" n="2">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>TEI encoding</item>
				</list>
			</change>
			<change who="#MW" when="2010-12-01" n="1">
				<label>Changed by</label>
				<name>Mary A. Waters</name>
				<list>
					<item>Created Edition</item>
				</list>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>
		<body>
			<div type="essay">
				<head><bibl><lb rendition="#center"/><author type="writer"><ref
								target="people.html#BarbauldMrs"><name>Anna Letitia
								Barbauld</name></ref></author>
						<lb rendition="#center"/><title type="main" level="a"><hi
								rendition="#smcaps">on novel writing</hi>.<lb rendition="#center"
								/><hi rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#BarbauldMrs">By
									Mrs. Barbauld.</ref></hi><hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
										><title level="j"><hi rendition="#italics">The Literary
											Magazine and American Register</hi></title> 2.15
									(December 1804): 693-698. The <title><hi rendition="#italics"
											>Literary Magazine and American Register</hi></title>
									was a semi-annual publication edited from 1803-1807 by <ref
										target="people.html#BrownCharles">Charles Brockden
										Brown</ref>. Readers may wish to compare this text with <ref
										target="people.html#BarbauldMrs">Barbauld</ref>&apos;s
									essays <title>&quot;The Life of <ref
											target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Samuel
											Richardson</ref>&quot;</title> (1804) and
										<title>&quot;On the Origin and Progress of
										Novel-Writing&quot;</title>
						(1810).</note></hi></title></bibl></head>
				<p> THERE is no period in the history of any nation, at all advanced in literature,
					in which fictitious narratives have not made a large part of the reading in
					which men have most delighted. They have been grafted on the actions of their
					heroes, interwoven with their mythology, moulded on the manners of the age, and,
					in return, have influenced not a little the manners of the next generation, by
					the principles they have inculcated, and the sensibilities they have exercised.
					A spirit of adventure, a high sense of honour, of martial glory, refined and
					romantic, sentimental delicacy, or all the enthusiasm of humanity, have been, in
					their turns, inspired by this powerful engine, which takes so strong a hold on
					the fancy and the passions of young readers. Accompanied with the embellishments
					of poetry, they produce the epic; concentrating the incidents, and exchanging
					story for action, they become dra-<pb n="694"/>matic; allied with some great
					moral or political end, didactic, as in the <title>Telemachus</title> of <ref
						target="people.html#FenelonFrancois">Fenelon</ref>, and the
						<title>Belisarius</title> of <ref target="people.html#Marmontel"
						>Marmontel</ref>. They are often the vehicles of satire, as in the
						<title>Candid</title> and <title>Baboue</title> of <ref
						target="people.html#Voltaire">Voltaire</ref>, and the
						<title>Gulliver</title> of <ref target="people.html#SwiftJonathan"
						>Swift</ref>. They take a tincture from the learning and politics of the
					times, and are often successfully employed to attack or to recommend the
					prevailing systems of the day. We have seen liberty and equality recommended by
					one performance, and ridiculed in another. When the range of this kind of
					writing is so extensive, and its efficacy so great, it is evidently entitled to
					hold no mean rank among the productions of genius; and, in truth, there is
					hardly any department of literature in which we shall meet with more fine
					writing than in the best productions of this kind. It is not easy, therefore, to
					say, why the poet should have so high a place allotted him in the temple of
					Fame, and the romance writer so low a one, as the general voice assigns him; for
					his dignity has by no means been measured by the pleasure he affords to his
					readers; yet the invention of a story, the choice of proper incidents, the
					modelling of a plan, the exhibition of character, the gradual unfolding of a
					plot, occasional beauties of description, and, above all, the power exercised
					over the reader&apos;s heart, by filling it with the emotions of love, pity,
					joy, anguish, transport, or indignation, together with the grave and affecting
					moral resulting from the whole, imply talents of the highest order, and ought to
					command our warmest praise. There is no walk in which taste and genius have more
					distinguished themselves, or in which virtuous and noble sentiments have been
					displayed with greater lustre, than in the splendid fictions, or pathetic tales,
					with which France, Germany, Switzerland, and England have adorned their
					literature. A history of romance, under all its forms, would be highly valuable,
					if given by a man of taste, and of ample reading. But there are some periods
					which form a new era in this kind of writing, and those productions particularly
					deserve our attention, which stand at the head of a class, and have diverted the
					taste of the public into some new channel. Of this kind are the writings of <ref
						target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref>. He may, in a great
					measure, be said to be the father of the modern novel of the serious or pathetic
					kind, and he was also original in the epistolary mode by which he carried on the
					story. </p>
				<p> Should we search among the treasures of ancient literature for fictions similar
					to the modern novel, we should find none more nearly resembling it than
						<title>&quot;Theagenes and Chariclea,&quot;</title> the work of <ref
						target="people.html#Heliodorus">Heliodorus</ref>, a christian bishop of
					Trieca, in Thessaly. Though his romance was unexceptionably pure and virtuous,
					he was required either to burn his book or resign his bishopric; upon which,
					with the heroism of an author, he chose the latter.</p>
				<p> But after Europe had sunk into barbarism, a taste was again to be formed; and a
					taste for the natural, the graceful, and the simply-pathetic is generally the
					last step in the progress of civilization.</p>
				<p> We know the character of the romances of chivalry....<title>Amadis de
						Gaul</title> at their head, with whose merits the English reader has lately
					been made acquainted, in an elegant abridged version.<hi rendition="#sup"><note
							place="foot"><hi rendition="#italics"><title>Amadis de
								Gaule</title></hi> is an early-sixteenth century romance by <ref
								target="people.html#RodriquezdeMontalvo">Rodr&#237;guez de
								Montalvo"</ref> with versions preceeding it by a century or more.
								<ref target="people.html#SoutheyRobert">Robert Southey</ref>&apos;s
							translation into English appeared in 1803. </note></hi> They were truly
					historical, but they heightened the traditionary adventures of heroes with
					marvellous tales of giants, enchantments, and other supernatural contrivances.
					But we must not suppose that even these fictions were always regarded, as we now
					regard them, as the mere play of fancy: &quot;<hi rendition="#italics">le vrai
						seul est aimable</hi>&quot; <hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"
							>&quot;the truth alone is beautiful&quot;; <ref
								target="people.html#Boileau">Boileau</ref>, <title><hi
									rendition="#italics">Epitre IX</hi></title> (1674) 43.
						</note></hi> was always so far a maxim, that no work of fancy can greatly
					succeed, which is not founded on popular belief: but what is truth? In ancient
					times, talismans, and sympathetic powders, and all-healing charms, were
					generally credited.</p>
				<p> Much love adventure was admitted into these narratives, but not always of the
					purest or most delicate <pb n="695"/>kind. Poetry was often made the vehicle,
					especially in Italy: <title><hi rendition="#italics">Orlando
						Furioso</hi></title><hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot">By <ref
								target="people.html#Ariosto">Ariosto</ref>.</note></hi> is a
					chivalrous romance in verse. </p>
				<p> As the spirit of warlike adventure subsided, these fictions softened, by
					degrees, into the languishing and amorous tales of the French school....into
						<title>Clelias</title> and <title>Cassandras</title>.<hi rendition="#sup"
							><note place="foot">Novels by <ref target="people.html#ScuderyMadeleine"
								>Mme. de Scud&#233;ry</ref> and <ref
								target="people.html#LaCalprenede">La Calpren&#232;de</ref>
							respectively.</note></hi> I might, indeed, have mentioned, before these,
					a romance of a peculiar kind, the <title>Astrea</title> of <ref
						target="people.html#UrfeHonored">d&apos; Urf&#233;</ref>, which all France
					read with eagerness, when first published. It is a pastoral romance, and its
					celebrity was owing to its abounding with allusions to the amours of the court
					of <ref target="people.html#HenryIVKingofFrance">Henry the fourth</ref>.</p>
				<p> The principle of these romances was high honour, impregnable chastity, a
					constancy unshaken by time or accident, and a species of love so exalted and
					refined, that it bore but little resemblance to a natural passion. In the story,
					they approached a step nearer to nature; the adventures were marvellous, but not
					impossible. Their personages were all remote from common life, and taken from
					ancient history, but without the least resemblance to the heroes whose names
					they bore. The manners, therefore, and the passions, referred to an ideal world,
					the creation of the writer; but the situations were often striking, and the
					sentiments always chaste and noble. They would have reigned longer, had they
					been less tedious. <ref target="people.html#Boileau">Boileau</ref> ridiculed
					these, as <ref target="people.html#Cervantes">Cervantes</ref> had done the
					others, and their knell was rung: people were ready to wonder they had ever
					admired them. </p>
				<p> A closer imitation of nature began now to be required: from the earliest times,
					however, there had been tales built upon real life, a few of them serious, but
					the greater part comic. The <title><hi rendition="#italics"
						>Decamerone</hi></title> of <ref target="people.html#Boccaccio"
						>Boccacio</ref>, the <title><hi rendition="#italics">Cent
						Nouvelles</hi></title> of the <ref target="people.html#MargueriteofNavarre"
						>queen of Navarre</ref>, <hi rendition="#italics">contes</hi> and <hi
						rendition="#italics">fableaux</hi> without number, may be considered as
					novels, though of a lighter texture: they abounded with adventure, generally of
					the humorous, often of the licentious kind, and, indeed, were mostly founded on
					amorous intrigues, while the nobler passions were seldom touched. The <title><hi
							rendition="#italics">Roman Comique</hi></title> of <ref
						target="people.html#Scarron">Scarron</ref> is a regular piece of its kind,
					and possesses great merit in the humorous way; but the <title><hi
							rendition="#italics">Zaide</hi></title> and the <title><hi
							rendition="#italics">Princesse de Cleves</hi></title> of <ref
						target="people.html#LaFayetteMadame">Madame de la Fayette</ref>, are deemed
					the first that approach the modern novel of the serious kind, the latter
					especially: they were written in the reign of <ref
						target="people.html#LouisXIVKingofFrance">Louis XIV</ref>, greatly admired,
					and considered as forming a new era in works of invention. <ref
						target="people.html#Voltaire">Voltaire</ref> says they were &quot;the first
					romances in which were seen natural incidents, and the manners of good company,
					described with elegance. Before her time, improbable adventures were related in
					a turgid and affected style.&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
								target="people.html#Voltaire">Voltaire</ref>, &quot;Ecrivains,
							don&apos;t plusieurs on illustr&#233; le si&#233;cle,&quot; one of a
							series of catalogs included in <title><hi rendition="#italics">Le Siecle
									de <ref target="people.html#LouisXIVKingofFrance">Louis
										XIV</ref></hi></title> (1751; London: R. Dodsley, 1752)
							2:486. Other editions position these catalogs differently.</note></hi>
					The novels of <ref target="people.html#LaFayetteMadame">Madame la Fayette</ref>
					are certainly beautiful, but a step is still wanting; they no longer speak,
					indeed, of <ref target="people.html#AlexandertheGreat">Alexander</ref>s and <ref
						target="people.html#BrutusMarcus">Brutus</ref>&apos;s, still less of giants
					and fairies; but the heroes and heroines are princes and princesses. They are
					not people of our acquaintance. The scene is perhaps in Spain, or among the
					Moors: it does not reflect the picture of domestic life, they are not the men
					and women we daily see about us.</p>
				<p>
					<hi rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#LeSageAlain">Le
						Sage</ref></hi>, in his <title><hi rendition="#italics">Gil
						Blas</hi></title>, a work of infinite diversion, though of dubious morality,
					presented us such people; but his portraits were mostly humorous, and his work
					was rather a series of separate adventures than a chain of events concurring to
					produce one catastrophe. There was still wanting a mode of writing which should
					connect the high passions and delicate sentiments of the old romance, with
					characters moving in our own sphere of life, and brought into action by events
					of daily occurrence. </p>
				<p> In the earlier periods of English history, we had our share of the rude
					literature of the times, and we were familiar, either in translations or works
					of our own growth, with <pb n="696"/>the heroes of chivalry, many of whom
					belonged to our own country. We had also, in common with our neighbours, the
					monkish legends, a species of romance abounding with the marvellous, and
					particularly suited to the taste of a superstitious age. Many of these merit
					attention as a considerable class of fictions: they have been justly exploded
					for their falsehood; they should not be preserved for their invention: they are
					now harmless: they can no longer excite our indignation; let them be permitted
					still to amuse our fancy. </p>
				<p> In the reign of <ref target="people.html#ElizabethIQueenofEngland">queen
						Elizabeth</ref>, we had the once famous romance, <hi rendition="#italics"
							><ref target="people.html#SidneyPhilip">Sidney</ref>&apos;s
							<title>Arcadia</title></hi>, of the pastoral heroic kind. It is a book
					that all have heard of, some few possess, but nobody reads. </p>
				<p> From that period, to the middle of the reign of <ref
						target="people.html#GeorgeIIKingofGreatBritain">George II</ref>, we had
					tales of various kinds, but scarcely one that is read at present, and, I
					believe, not any except that ingenious allegory, <title><hi rendition="#italics"
							>The Pilgrim&apos;s Progress</hi></title>, that was known out of
					England. We had poets and philosophers long before we attained excellence in the
					lighter kinds of prosaic composition. <ref target="people.html#HarringtonJames"
						>Harrington</ref>&apos;s <title><hi rendition="#italics">Oceana</hi></title>
					is political, and will grievously disappoint those who seek amusement in it. The
							<title><hi rendition="#italics">Atalantis</hi></title> of <ref
						target="people.html#ManleyMrs">Mrs. Manly</ref> lives only in that line of
						<ref target="people.html#PopeAlexander">Pope</ref> which promises it
					immortality: <quote><lg type="stanza">
							<l>As long as <title>Atalantis</title> shall be read.<hi
									rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><ref
											target="people.html#PopeAlexander">Alexander
										Pope</ref>&apos;s comment on <title><hi rendition="#italics"
												>The New Atalantis</hi></title> (1709) by <ref
											target="people.html#ManleyMrs">Delariviere Manley</ref>
										appears in <title><hi rendition="#italics">The Rape of the
												Lock</hi></title>, Canto III, line
								165.</note></hi></l>
						</lg></quote> It was, like <title>Astrea</title>, filled with fashionable
					scandal. <ref target="people.html#BehnAphra">Mrs. Behn</ref>&apos;s novels were
					licentious: they are also extinct. Till the middle of the last century,
					theatrical productions and poetry made a greater part of polite reading than
					novels, which had not attained either elegance or nice discrimination of
					characters; some maritime or some love adventure were all they aimed at. The
					ladies&apos; library, described in the <title>Spectator</title>, contains
						&quot;<title>the Grand Cyrus</title>, with a pin stuck in one of the leaves,
					and <title>Clelia</title>, which opened of itself in the place that describes
					two lovers in a bower;&quot;<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><title><hi
									rendition="#italics">Spectator</hi></title> No. 37 (Thursday,
							April 12, 1711). The novels are by <ref target="people.html#UrfeHonored"
								>d&apos;Urf&#233;</ref> and <ref
								target="people.html#ScuderyMadeleine">Mme. de
							Scud&#233;ry</ref>.</note></hi> but there does not occur either there,
					or, I believe, in any other part of the work, the name of one English novel, the
						<title>Atalantis</title> excepted. Plays are often mentioned as a favourite
					and dangerous part of ladies&apos; reading. </p>
				<p> The first author who distinguished himself by natural painting was that truly
					original genius <ref target="people.html#DefoeDaniel">De Foe</ref>; and if from
					any one <ref target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref> caught his
					peculiar manner of writing, to him it must be traced, whose <title><hi
							rendition="#italics">Robinson Crusoe</hi></title> and <title><hi
							rendition="#italics">Family Instructor</hi></title>, the latter
					consisting of domestic dialogues, he must have read in his youth. Both were
					accurate describers, minute and circumstantial, but the minuteness of <ref
						target="people.html#DefoeDaniel">De Foe</ref> was displayed in things, and
					that of <ref target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref> in persons
					and sentiments. No one knew, like <ref target="people.html#DefoeDaniel">De
						Foe</ref>, to give to fiction the air of truth, by an accumulation of
					circumstance, and a natural style of narration, unless, indeed, he were rivalled
					by <ref target="people.html#SwiftJonathan">Swift</ref>, in his
						<title>Gulliver</title> and John Bull. <ref target="people.html#DefoeDaniel"
						>De Foe</ref> wrote also other tales, which I have not seen: they do not
					appear to have attained much celebrity. <ref
						target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref> was the man who was
					born to introduce a new kind of moral painting: he drew equally from nature and
					from his own thoughts. From the world about him he took incidents, manners, and
					general character; and from his own imagination he copied that sublime of
					virtue, which charms us in <ref target="people.html#ClarissaHarlowe"
						>Clarissa</ref>, and that sublime of passion, which subdues us in <ref
						target="people.html#Clementina">Clementina</ref>. That kind of fictitious
					writing, of which he has set the example, disclaims all aid from giants or
					genii. The moated castle gives place to a modern parlour; the princess and her
					pages to a lady and her domestics, or even to a rustic maid, without birth or
					fortune; we are not called on to wonder at improbable events, but to be moved by
					natural passions, and impressed by salutary maxims. The pathos of the story, and
					the dignity of the sentiments, interest and <pb n="697"/>charm us; simplicity is
					warned, vice rebuked; and from the perusal of a fiction we rise better prepared
					to meet calamity with firmness, and to perform our respective parts on the great
					theatre of life. It was the high and just praise given by our great critic, Dr.
						<ref target="#JohnsonSamuel">Johnson</ref>, to this author, that he had
					enlarged the knowledge of human nature, and taught the passions to move at the
					command of virtue.<hi rendition="#sup"><note place="foot"><title><hi
									rendition="#italics">Rambler</hi></title> 97 (Tuesday, February
							19, 1751).</note></hi> The novelist has, indeed, all the advantage of
					the preacher in introducing useful maxims and sentiments of virtue; an advantage
					which <ref target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref> made large use
					of; and he has besides the power of impressing them upon the heart, through the
					best sensibilities of our nature. <ref target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel"
						>Richardson</ref> prided himself on being a moral and religious writer; and,
					as <ref target="people.html#AddisonJoseph">Addison</ref> did before him, he
					professed to take under his particular protection that sex which is supposed to
					be the most open to good or evil impressions, whose inexperience most requires
					cautionary precepts, and whose sensibilities it is most important to secure
					against a wrong direction. The manner of this captivating writer was also new. </p>
				<p> There are three modes of carrying on a story: the narrative, or epic, as it may
					be called; in this the author himself relates the whole adventure: this is the
					manner of <ref target="people.html#Cervantes">Cervantes</ref>, in his <title>Don
						Quixote</title>, and of <ref target="people.html#FieldingHenry"
						>Fielding</ref>, in his <title>Tom Jones</title>. It is the most common way.
					The author, like the muse, is supposed to know every thing; he can reveal the
					secret springs of actions, and let us into events in his own time and manner. He
					can be concise or diffuse, according as the different parts of his story require
					it. He can indulge, as <ref target="people.html#FieldingHenry">Fielding</ref>
					does, in digressions and reflections, and thus deliver sentiments, and display
					knowledge, which would not properly belong to any of the characters. But his
					narration will not be lively, except he frequently drops himself, and runs into
					dialogue: all good writers, therefore, have thrown as much as possible of the
					dramatic into their narrative. <ref target="people.html#BurneyFanny">Mad.
						d&apos; Arblay</ref> has done this so successfully, that we have as clear an
					idea, not only of the sentiments, but the manner of expression of her different
					personages, as if we took it from the scenes of a play.</p>
				<p> Another mode is that of memoirs, where the hero of the adventure relates his own
					story. <hi rendition="#italics"><ref target="people.html#SmollettTobias"
							>Smollet</ref></hi>, in his <title><hi rendition="#italics">Roderick
							Random</hi></title>, and <hi rendition="#italics"><ref
							target="people.html#GoldsmithOliver">Goldsmith</ref></hi>, in his
							<title><hi rendition="#italics">Vicar of Wakefield</hi></title>, have
					adopted this mode: it confines the author&apos;s style, which ought to be,
					though it is not always, suited to the capacity and education of the imaginary
					narrator. It has the warmth and interest a person may be supposed to feel in
					relating his own concerns, and he can more gracefully dwell upon minute
					circumstances. It has a greater air of truth, and it seems to account for the
					communication to the public. The author, it is true, knows every thing; but,
					when the secret recesses of the heart are to be laid open, we can hear no one
					with so much pleasure as the actor himself. <hi rendition="#italics"><ref
							target="people.html#Marivaux">Marivaux</ref></hi>, a contemporary of
						<ref target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref>, has put the
					history of Marianne into her own mouth, and we are amused to hear her dwell on
					little touches, which are almost too trivial to be noticed by any body but
					herself. </p>
				<p> But what the hero cannot say, the author cannot tell, nor can it be rendered
					probable, that a very circumstantial narrative should be given by a person,
					perhaps at the close of a long life, of conversations that have happened at the
					beginning of it. The author has always two characters to support, and has to
					consider how his hero felt during his adventures, and how it is natural he
					should feel when only relating them; at a period, perhaps, when curiosity is
					extinct, passions cool, and when, at any rate, the suspenses which kept pace
					with them are over. This seems, therefore, the least perfect mode of any.</p>
				<p> A third way is that of epistola-<pb n="698"/>ry correspondence, carried on
					between the persons of the story.... This is the form used by <ref
						target="people.html#RichardsonSamuel">Richardson</ref>, and many others
					after, but by none before him. He seems to have been led to it by some
					circumstances in his early youth. This method unites the advantages of the other
					two; it gives the feelings of the moment, as the writers felt them at the
					moment. It allows a pleasing variety of style, if the author has sufficient
					command of language to assume it. It makes the work dramatic, since all the
					characters speak in their own persons. It accounts for chasms in the story, by
					the probable omission or loss of letters. It is inconsistent with a rapid style,
					but gives room for the graceful introduction of remarks and sentiments, or
					almost any kind of digressive matter. But, on the other hand, it is highly
					incredible; it is the <hi rendition="#italics">most natural</hi> and the <hi
						rendition="#italics">least probable</hi> way of telling a story. That
					letters should be written at all times, and upon every occasion in life, that
					those letters should be preserved, and altogether form a connected story, it
					requires much art to render probable. It introduces the inconvenience so much
					felt in dramatic writing, for want of a narrator; the necessity of having an
					insipid confidant to tell those circumstances to, that an author can introduce
					in no other way. It obliges a man to tell of himself, what shame or modesty
					would suffer no man to tell; and when a long conversation is repeated, supposes
					a memory more exact than is generally found. Artificial as it is, still it
					enables an author to assume, in a lively manner, the hopes, and fears, and
					passions, and to imitate the peculiar way of thinking and speaking of his
					characters, and has been adopted by many, both at home and abroad, especially by
					the French writers; their language, perhaps, being particularly suited to the
					epistolary style, and <hi rendition="#italics"><ref
							target="people.html#RousseauJeanJacques">Rousseau</ref></hi> himself, in
					his <title><hi rendition="#italics">Nouvelle Heloise</hi></title>, has followed
					the steps of our countryman. </p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
